But one of the clusters we want to show you very quickly is this amazing cluster of portraits that we found from museums around the world. If you could zoom in a little bit more, Cyril. Just to show you, you can just travel through portraits. And essentially, you can do nature, you can do horses and clusters galore. When we saw all these portraits, we were like, "Hey, can we do something fun for kids, or can we do something playful to get people interested in portraits?" Because I haven't really seen young kids really excited to go to a portrait gallery. I wanted to try to figure something out. So we created something called the portrait matcher. It's quite self-explanatory, so I'm just going to let Cyril show his beautiful face. And essentially what's happening is, with the movement of his head, we are matching different portraits around the world from museums. (Applause) And I don't know about you, but I've shown it to my nephew and sister, and the reaction is just phenomenal. All they ask me is, "When can we go see this?" And by the way, if we're nice, maybe, Cyril, you can smile and find a happy one? Oh, perfect. By the way, this is not rehearsed. Congrats, Cyril. Great stuff. Oh wow. OK, let's move on; otherwise, this will just take the whole time. (Applause) So, art and culture can be fun also, right? For our last quick experiment -- we call all of these "experiments" -- our last quick experiment comes back to machine learning. We show you clusters, visual clusters, but what if we could ask the machine to also name these clusters? What if it could automatically tag them, using no actual metadata? So what we have is this kind of explorer, where we have managed to match, I think, around 4,000 labels. And we haven't really done anything special here, just fed the collection. And we found interesting categories. We can start with horses, a very straightforward category. You would expect to see that the machine has put images of horses, right? And it has, but you also notice, right over there, that it has a very abstract image that it has still managed to recognize and cluster as horses. We also have an amazing head in terms of a horse. And each one has the tags as to why it got categorized in this. So let's move to another one which I found very funny and interesting, because I don't understand how this category came up. It's called "Lady in Waiting." If, Cyril, you do it very quickly, you will see that we have these amazing images of ladies, I guess, in waiting or posing. I don't really understand it. But I've been trying to ask my museum contacts, you know, "What is this? What's going on here?" And it's fascinating. Coming back to gold very quickly, I wanted to search for gold and see how the machine tagged all the gold. But, actually, it doesn't tag it as gold. We are living in popular times. It tags it as "bling-bling." (Laughter) I'm being hard on Cyril, because I'm moving too fast. Essentially, here you have all the bling-bling of the world's museums organized for you. And finally, to end this talk and these experiments, what I hope you feel after this talk is happiness and emotion. And what would we see when we see happiness? If we actually look at all the objects that have been tagged under "happiness," you would expect happiness, I guess. But there was one that came up that was very fascinating and interesting, which was this artwork by Douglas Coupland, our friend and artist in residence as well, called, "I Miss My Pre-Internet Brain." I don't know why the machine feels like it misses its pre-Internet brain and it's been tagged here, but it's a very interesting thought. I sometimes do miss my pre-Internet brain, but not when it comes to exploring arts and culture online. So take out your phones, take out your computers, go visit museums. And just a quick call-out to all the amazing archivists, historians, curators, who are sitting in museums, preserving all this culture. And the least we can do is get our daily dose of art and culture for ourselves and our kids. Thank you. (Applause)
Uno de los grupos que mostraré muy rápidamente es este increíble grupo de retratos que encontramos en los museos de todo el mundo. Si pudieras aumentar un poco más, Cyril. Solo para mostrarles, Uds. pueden simplemente viajar por los retratos. Y, esencialmente, pueden ir a naturaleza, caballos y múltiples combinaciones. Cuando vimos todos estos retratos, pensamos: "¿Podemos hacer algo divertido para los niños, o algo lúdico para que la gente se interese en los retratos?". Porque no he visto niños pequeños realmente entusiasmados con ir a una galería de retratos. Quería encontrar algo mejor. Por eso hemos creado algo llamado comparador de retratos. Es bastante autoexplicativo, por eso dejaré que Cyril muestre su hermoso rostro. Y esencialmente lo que sucede es, que mediante el movimiento de la cabeza, comparamos diferentes retratos de los museos de todo el mundo. (Aplausos) Y yo no sé Uds., pero le he mostrado esto a mi sobrino y hermana, y su reacción es simplemente fenomenal. Todo lo que me preguntan es, "¿Cuándo podemos ir a ver esto?". Y, por cierto, si somos amables, tal vez, Cyril, ¿puedes sonreír y encontrar una cara feliz? Oh, perfecto. Por cierto, esto no se ensaya. Felicidades, Cyril. Buena cosa. Oh guau. Sigamos, de lo contrario, esto acabará con todo mi tiempo. (Aplausos) Por lo tanto, el arte y la cultura también pueden ser divertidos, ¿no? Para nuestro último experimento rápido --llamamos a todos estos "experimentos"-- nuestro último experimento rápido vuelve al aprendizaje automático. Les mostramos los grupos, los grupos visuales, pero ¿y si pedimos a la máquina nombrar también estas agrupaciones? ¿Qué pasa si se etiquetaran automáticamente sin metadatos reales? Así que lo que tenemos es este tipo de explorador, donde hemos logrado emparejar, creo que, alrededor de 4000 etiquetas. Y no hemos hecho nada realmente especial aquí, simplemente alimentar la colección. Y encontramos categorías interesantes. Podemos empezar con caballos, una categoría muy sencilla. Se podría esperar ver que la máquina ha puesto imágenes de caballos, ¿no? Y sí, pero también se dio cuenta, justo allí, que tiene una imagen muy abstracta que ha podido reconocer y agrupar como caballos. También tenemos una cabeza increíble relacionada con caballo. Y cada una tiene las etiquetas de por qué se clasificó así. Pasemos a otro que me pareció muy divertido e interesante, porque no entiendo cómo se generó esta categoría. Se llama "Dama de compañía". Si, Cyril, lo haces rápidamente, verán que tenemos imágenes sorprendentes de damas, supongo, esperando o posando. Yo realmente no entiendo. Pero he intentado preguntar a mis contactos de los museos, "¿Qué es esto? ¿Qué está pasando aquí?". Y es fascinante. Volviendo al oro muy rápidamente, quería buscar el oro y ver cómo la máquina etiquetaba todo el oro. Pero, en realidad, no lo etiqueta como oro. Vivimos en tiempos populares. y lo etiqueta como "bling-bling". (Risas) Estoy siendo pesado con Cyril, porque me estoy moviendo muy rápido. En esencia, aquí está todo el bling-bling de todos los museos del mundo organizados para Uds. Y para terminar con esta charla y estos experimentos, lo que espero que sientan tras esta charla es felicidad y emoción. Y ¿qué veríamos al mirar la felicidad? Si nos fijamos en todos los objetos que han sido etiquetados como "felicidad" uno esperaría felicidad, supongo. Pero hubo uno emergió que era muy fascinante e interesante, era la obra de Douglas Coupland, nuestro amigo y artista también lo llama "Añoro mi cerebro preinternetiano". No sé por qué la máquina siente que añora su cerebro anterior a Internet y se ha etiquetado aquí, pero es una idea muy interesante. A veces echo de menos mi cerebro preinternetiano, pero no cuando exploro arte y cultura en línea. Así que saquen sus teléfonos, saquen sus computadoras, visiten museos. Y solo una rápida llamada a todos los increíbles archiveros historiadores, curadores, sentados en los museos, preservando toda esta cultura. Y lo menos que podemos hacer es obtener una dosis diaria de arte y cultura para nosotros y para nuestros hijos. Gracias. (Aplausos)